<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>stats on They call me Brett</title>
    <link>https://brettviren.github.io/tags/stats/</link>
    <description>Recent content in stats on They call me Brett</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://brettviren.github.io/tags/stats/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Vaccine Effectiveness</title>
      <link>https://brettviren.github.io/posts/vaccine-effectiveness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://brettviren.github.io/posts/vaccine-effectiveness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have seen the quantitiy &lt;em&gt;vaccine effectiveness&lt;/em&gt; (VE) used in many
contexts and never really knew what it meant.  Today, I checked and
this is what I learned.  As I sort of expected, the causal connection
with the workings of the vaccine is not complete.  It leaves some room
to be influenced things that are merely correlated with being
vaccinated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NY state gov has some good info on &lt;a href=&#34;https://coronavirus.health.ny.gov/covid-19-breakthrough-data&#34;&gt;vaccine breakthrough&lt;/a&gt;.  Currently
4.9% of vaxxed NYers caught COVID.  If you are vaxxed and catch it,
you&amp;rsquo;ll contribute to only 0.15% of hospitalized COVID patients.  On
the topic of hospitalization, the page continues with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the week of May 3, 2021, the estimated vaccine effectiveness shows
fully-vaccinated New Yorkers had a 92.4% lower chance of becoming a
COVID-19 case, compared to unvaccinated New Yorkers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, 92.4 seems like a nice happy big number, great!&amp;hellip;  But then,
&amp;ldquo;%-lower chance&amp;rdquo;, that just sounds weird to me.  What does it mean?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That page conveniently links to the open article &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa2116063&#34;&gt;Rosenberg et all, Dec
2021&lt;/a&gt; which conveniently links to the even more useful &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nejm.org/doi/suppl/10.1056/NEJMoa2116063/suppl%5Ffile/nejmoa2116063%5Fappendix.pdf&#34;&gt;appendix&lt;/a&gt; which
defines&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[HR = \frac{h_{vaxxed}(t)}{h_{nasty}(t)}\]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, those are my subscripts.  The \(h(t)\) here is the called the
&lt;em&gt;hazard function&lt;/em&gt; which is apparently a term-of-art.  To the google!
That turns up these very clear and concise &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.stanford.edu/~lutian/coursepdf/unit1.pdf&#34;&gt;note&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.stanford.edu/~lutian/coursepdf/slideweek1.pdf&#34;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; from
a Stanford bio class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is explained that the &lt;em&gt;hazard function&lt;/em&gt; is a conditional
probability that some &amp;ldquo;event&amp;rdquo; (catching COVID) will occur for a time
\(T \in [t,t+dt]\) given that the event had yet to occur by time \(T=t\).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a daily hazard function can tell us the probability we
get COVID tomorrow given we don&amp;rsquo;t have it today. (Maybe it should be
called the Wimpy Hamburger Function).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Stanford continues to define a &lt;em&gt;survival function&lt;/em&gt; and various
relations between it, a &lt;em&gt;cumulative hazard function&lt;/em&gt;, the original PDF
and the hazard function.  But, I leave it there and go back to the NY
State report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There it gives this example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;cohort size&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;\(N_c=215,159\) vaxxed people at risk in first week of May&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;infected&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;\(N_i = 56\) number of vaxxed infected in first week of May&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It defines the hazard function for that cohort that week as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[h(t) = \frac{N_i}{N_c - \frac{N_i}{2}}\]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where the \(\frac{1}{2}\) in the denominator is apparently an attempt to
place the measure at the middle of the week (?).  Ie, half the
infected are removed from cohort.  That looks a little weird to me,
but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t change the result much as long as \(N_i \ll N_c\) so
whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collected data gives \(h_{vaxxed} = 3.68\) per 100,000 people for that
first month of May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that week the nasty unvaxxed saw an \(N_c\) about 10x larger and
\(N_i\) is 100x larger so \(h_{nasty} = 35.80\) per 100,000 is 10x more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then an intermediate &lt;em&gt;hazard ratio&lt;/em&gt; of those two functions, \(HR = 0.103\)
and finally the &lt;em&gt;vax effectiveness&lt;/em&gt; of 89.7%,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[VE = 1-HR\]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To calculate the VE for the next week we do the same thing after
reducing the number of cohorts by how many got COVID during the
current week: \(N^{w+1}_c = N^w_c - N^w_i\).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that, VE is simply and effectively (one minus) a double
ratio of the relative infected fractions between vaxxed and unvaxxed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, knowing the definition it is clear to me that we are making a
small category error by attributing this measure of &amp;ldquo;effectiveness&amp;rdquo; to
just the mechanism of the vaccine.  There must be other, unknown (to
me at least), contributions that are correlated with being vaccinated.
For example, people that get vaxxed must also be more likely to wear
masks, socially distance and engage in other behavior that counters
the spread of the virus.  All those activities will keep their
relative infections lower than their nastier counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what?  Well, not much.  Mostly I don&amp;rsquo;t like so much attention payed
to undefined numbers.  But also, there is a potential curiosity of
statistics we are missing.  Faced with two choices, say two types of
vaccines, we might want to know more about these correlations to see
if they might break the tie for which choice is best for our personal
choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say, just for sake of example, Pfizer and Moderna had the same VE as
defined above.  Now let&amp;rsquo;s pretend we knew that &amp;ldquo;Pfizer people&amp;rdquo; were
much more into masks and social distancing.  That would mean that
Moderna must be a better vaccine in order for the two to have an equal
VE.  We might then decide personally to get Modernal and mask up and
distance socially.  Again, just a fabricated example.  I&amp;rsquo;m not saying
one vax is better or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, I&amp;rsquo;m also definitely not saying don&amp;rsquo;t get vaxxed.  Get vaxxed, you
filthy swine!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
